A Guide to the College of Education Restructuring Records, 1979-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
College of Education Restructuring Records 1979-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2006-020
3 containers; 3.0 cu. ft.
Publicly circulated e-mails, reports, and meeting handouts that served as major communications during the restructuring of Virginia Tech's College of Education. Also contains transcripts of speeches given by officials as well as some meetings, and field notes by Jan Nespor of meetings with the "task forces." Also contains materials relating to the immediate response to Virginia Tech President Paul Torgersen's decision and the early planning for the merger with the College of Human Resources. The records essentially stop after January 1996.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The College of Education Restructuring Records were donated to Special Collections in 2006.
Historical Information
In 1990, the state of Virginia began to cut funding to higher education. During the first phase of these cuts, Virginia Tech responded with general reductions across colleges. By 1993, however, the university had entered "Phase II," which called for further budget cuts, to be based on strategic decisions about where the university should be allocating its resources:
The phrase "Phase II" is intended to signify the transition to a more thoughtful period of review, restructuring, and renewal. In Phase II we will replace opportunism and expediency with a planned approach involving the entire university community in a careful analysis of options and priorities. (Phase II document from provost's office, 1993-09-24, pg. 1)
A plan introduced in 1993 directed that have every college submit a "reallocation plan" at the beginning of each biennium. These plans were to describe a permanent reduction of 1.5% in each college's base budget (for the College of Education (COE) 1993 budget, a cut of approximately $125,000). University administration would then reallocate the expropriated money, giving priority to such things as:
Faculty salaries, graduate student stipends, and the host of new regulatory requirements we must address. The scale of this reallocation may need to increase if we are successful in stemming the decline in state support for higher education. (From Phase II document, "Accepting Greater Responsibility for our Own Destiny," 1993-10-4, pg. 10)
In January 1994, the provost rejected the reduction plan submitted by the College of Education and called for a new draft plan in 10 weeks, stipulating that the plan should detail how the college would reduce its budget by 20% (about $1.6 million) over the next three years. As he explained:
This [cut] is not really abut enrollments, not really about weighted student credit hours, it is not about any other standard measures you come up... it's not really about quality - so much as, what I'm talking about today is the matter of mission and priorities, and in that sense a matter of focus, a real sharpening up of the College's fundamental purpose. [A full transcript of the provost's remarks can be found within the collection.]
Coupled with the previous three years of state-driven budget cuts, this new proposed reduction would shrink the faculty of the college by 20 or 30 positions, programs would be shut down, and tenured faculty might be laid off.
The cuts to Virginia Tech's College of Education were similar to those experienced at other institutions of higher learning. Colleges and schools of education lack powerful alumni and constituencies, rarely have access to large, steady streams of government funding, and enroll more women and minorities than most other fields. These factors put them in structurally weak positions within universities. As Slaughter (1993) points out, across the U.S., education "was cut more deeply than almost any other field in the 1980s" (pg. 272) and accounted for about 37% of all faculty dismissals during that period (pg. 270).
As the faculty of Tech's College of Education scrambled to address the new mandates, Jan Nespor was asked, as the College's only ethnographer, to study or "monitor" the restructuring process. (Within the first box of the collection are e-mails relating to Nespor's status as archivist.)
After about 20 months of intensive planning for restructuring the College of Education, Virginia Tech President Paul Torgersen decided that the college would instead be dissolved and merged with the College of Human Resources. As he explained:
"There are a lot of colleges of education, schools of education out there. A [university governing] Board member asked... 'Why do we even have college of education? Radford [nearby Radford University] was set up as a teachers' college. It's 15-17 miles away, why don't you consider closing the College of Education?' ... I read only a couple of days ago, a member of the House of Delegates who was re-elected from Danville, was questioning whether we need all these colleges of education.
I'm sorry that you're caught up in this, but part of it is symbolic. What the university is doing is saying "We had nine colleges, we now have eight." And believe me, that's going to be applauded across this Commonwealth like you can't believe. And the university needs support." [Full transcript contained within the collection.]
Having been forced 22 months earlier to terminate programs which were deemed irrelevant, such as adult education, the college was paired in the new College of Human Resources and Education with such unlikely partners as Hotel and Tourism Management and Interior Design. In 2003, the College of Human Resources and Education was in turn combined with most of the liberal arts departments from the former College of Arts and Sciences to form Virginia Tech's College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences.
Scope and Content
This collection contains records relating to the restructuring of Virginia Tech's College of Education and includes reviews of existing programs, task forces on revising the governance structure of the college and its curriculum. The collection primarily contains the publicly circulated e-mails, reports, and meeting handouts that served as major communications during the restructuring. There are also transcripts of speeches given by officials as well as some meetings, and a few descriptive field notes written by restructuring monitor Jan Nespor of things like "task forces." Anything pertaining to personnel issues has been omitted as have e-mails or other reports or communications that might reasonably be considered confidential. Although the archives contain materials relating to the immediate response to Virginia Tech President Paul Torgersen's decision and the early planning for the merger with the College of Human Resources, they essentially stop after January 1996.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in a roughly chronological order.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Related documents (e.g., relating to Phase I and Phase II of the university's restructuring) should be available within the appropriate University Archives Record Groups.
Contents List
- NCATE institutional report 1979 (Box-folder 1-1)
- Miscellaneous field notes 1994-1995 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Memos related to Nespor's monitoring of restructuring 1994-1995 (Box-folder 1-3)
- Interviews by Liz Roth Mar-Apr 1995 (Box-folder 1-3a)
  Disks and transcripts of interviews with Dr. John Burton, Dr. Susie Murphy, and Dr. Sue Magliaro - concerning experiences with College of Education restructuring
- Constitution and by-laws 1998 (Box-folder 4)
  - Constitution and by-laws of COE Faculty Association Oct 21 1988
  - By-laws of COE Classified Staff Association n.d.
- Budget cuts 1990 (Box-folder 1-5)
- Alumni Association report on budget problems 1993 (Box-folder 1-6)
- College of Education - annual reports 1990-1994 (Box-folder 1-7)
- University plan 1991-1996 (Box-folder 1-8)
- University Forum on Liberal Education 1992 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Report of the University Forum on Liberal Education Jan 23 1992
- Faculty work assignments 1993 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Memo from Dean Buffer to faculty Jan 20 1993
- Planning chronology 1990-1994 (Box-folder 1-11)
- College of Education restructuring plans Fall 1993 (Box-folder 1-12-12c)
  - Multiple drafts of COE plan 1993-1998
- Other restructuring plans 1981-1993 (Box-folder 1-13-13b)
  Restructuring plans from other universities: Oregon State (1992), University of Minnesota (1982), University of Michigan (1984), University of New Mexico, (1992), University of Tulsa, (1984), University of Pittsburgh (1991), University of Maryland at College Park (1992), Penn State (1993), University of California (1993), Ohio State University (January 1994)
- Virginia Tech Administrative Fact Book Fall 1993 (Box-folder 1-14)
- College of Education - graduate / undergraduate students, FTE and headcount Fall 1993 (Box-folder 1-15)
- Bureau of Educational Services 1994 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Summary of research consortium surveys 1994
  - Draft, "Bureau of Educational Services" Mar 29 1994
- E-Mail and memos prior to provost's announcement 1994 (Box-folder 1-17)
  Memos containing information about reasons behind restructuring and recommendations for early restructuring plans.
- Provost's demands 1994 (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Transcript of provost's remarks Feb 1 1994
  - COE faculty meeting minutes Feb 3 1994
- Restructuring updates 1994-1995 (Box-folder 1-19)
- E-mails Feb 2-6 1994 (Box-folder 1-20)
- Scheduling return of funds 1994 (Box-folder 1-21)
- E-mails Feb 7-9 1994 (Box-folder 1-22)
  - Minutes of Planning Group meeting Feb 8 1994
  - Notes from informational staff meeting Feb 8 1994
  - Draft of Planning Committee memo on mission and focus of college Feb 8 1994
- Buffer's resignation 1994 (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Transcript of Buffer's farewell speech
- Meeting with students Feb 10 1994 (Box-folder 1-24)
  - Notes by S. Kimball
  - Notes by C. Metcalf
- E-mails and memos Feb 13-18 1994 (Box-folder 1-25)
  Memo and e-mails on College of Education, including the provost's meeting with College of Education's faculty, information about Worner being appointed interim dean, time-line for preparation of preliminary plan, minutes of Planning Group meeting
- E-mails and memos Feb 23-Mar 2 1994 (Box-folder 1-26)
  - Report on meeting from Sherman to Worner
  - Copy of Dean Bates' handout at meeting
  - Minutes of Planning Group meeting
  - Handouts from Jim Hoerner
  - Minutes from Planning Group meeting (Holford)
- Action teams Feb-Mar 1994 (Box-folder 1-27)
  - Jim Hoerner's "Points for Consideration..."
  - Draft of COE mission statement
  - Draft of mission statement
  - Draft from Wildman on mission statement
- Planning meeting and mission statement Mar 1994 (Box-folder 1-28)
  - Summary from Creative Proposals Task Group: Steve Parsons, "Defining K-12 Schooling;" George Graham, "Suggestion for a 21st Century Approach to Student Teacher Supervision;" Robertshaw, "Administrative Functions"
  - Minutes Mar 8 1994
  - Robertshaw, "What to Tell Students"
- First draft of restructuring plan 1994 (Box-folder 1-29)
  - Worner's draft plan for COE
  - Robertshaw on early retirement / buy out
- Planning meeting Mar 16 1994 (Box-folder 1-30)
  - Notes from planning meeting (Holford)
  - Transcript of meeting
- Planning meeting Mar 25 1994 (Box-folder 1-31)
  - Minutes of meeting (Holford)
  - Materials distributed at meeting
    - Anonymous letter to Worner
    - Memo from Jim Wolfe on academic priorities
    - Memo from Carlisle on academic priorities and Phase II
    - Memo from Joshia Tlou on international education in the COE mission statement
    - Memo from Gabriella Belli on COE reorganization plan
    - Letter from Belli, Boucouvalas, Stubblefield & Wiswell with proposal for Northern Virginia Campus reorganization
    - Memo from Daisy Stewart with memo from VTE Administrative Unit Three over "Another View" on college restructuring
    - Memo from Jim Hoerner on future mission and direction of COE
- Exercise physiology transfer 1994 (Box-folder 1-32)
- Planning meeting Apr 1 1994 (Box-folder 1-33)
  - Discussion notes (Metcalf)
  - Minutes of Planning Group meeting (Metcalf)
  - "Planning for Work Teams" worksheet
  - Schedule of upcoming events (Apr 15-Jul 1)
- Executive Committee meeting Apr 15 1994 (Box-folder 1-34)
  - Preliminary plan for restructuring
  - Table 1 handout on 1993-4 FTE resource allocations and approved 1997-98 allocations
  - Appendices to preliminary plan
  - Work team worksheet
  - Minutes
- Reorganization information manual Apr 1994 (Box-folder 1-34a)
- Outside stakeholders' responses to April 15 plan (Box-folder 1-35)
  - Memo from Worner: "Request for External Review of Preliminary Plan"
  - Worner on response to VCCS chancellor's response to plan and letter from chancellor
- Announcement of Provost Carlisle's departure Apr 1994 (Box-folder 1-36)
  - Memo from Torgersen to university staff Apr 26 1994
  - Announcement of Dec 9 reception honoring Carlisle n.d.
- C & I faculty meetings Fall 1994 (Box-folder 1-37)
  - Meeting agenda Aug 18 1994
  - Rough notes from meeting (Nespor)
  - Official minutes (Glasson)
- Foundations Program 1994 (Box-folder 1-38-38b)
  - Draft of program profile
- Task force reports Jun 1994 (Box-folder 2-39)
- Steering Committee 1994 (Box-folder 2-40)
  - Notes from Steering Committee meeting
  - Directory of Steering Committee members
- Meetings of dean's staff and division directors 1994 (Box-folder 2-41)
  - Memo from Worner to OOD staff on "Restructuring, Next Stage Planning - Update"
  - Memo from Worner on "Provost's Meeting with Deans and DD Meeting Follow-up," including "Report from Janet Johnson to Deans, 5-25"
  - Memo from Worner on "Dean's Meeting," with attachments
  - Memo from Gordon Davies et al to General Professional Advisory Committee on "Restructuring Plans"
  - "Notes on Restructuring VPI&SU"
- Worner memo on "Political and Strategic Planning" May 13 1994 (Box-folder 2-42)
- Admission trends and parent focus groups May 20 1994 (Box-folder 2-43)
- Task force functions and memberships 1994 (Box-folder 2-44)
- Governance and Organization Task Force Summer 1994 (Box-folder 2-45-45a)
  - College of Education organizational chart Feb 1994
  - Official meeting minutes May 4 1994
  - Rough meeting notes by Jan Nespor May 4 1994
  - Statement of task force's charge
  - List of "Critical Values" within COE mission
  - Memo from D. Robertshaw on retreat
  - Retreat agenda
  - Outline of G&O Task Force report
  - Memo from Parks announcing draft of task force report
  - Draft of G&O Task Force report
- Governance and Organization Task Force 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2-46)
  - Agenda for Governance and Organization Task Force meeting
  - Memo to COE faculty announcing meetings for 1994-1995
  - Agenda for meeting
  - Statement of task force mission
  - Statement of Task Force Steering Committee's seven issues
  - Chronology of restructuring events
  - Partial transcript of meeting
- Curriculum Task Force 1994 (Box-folder 2-47-47b)
  - Curriculum Task Force report
  - Copy of program planning documents Jul 1 1994
  - Memo from Worner re-defining charge of Curriculum Committee
  - Memo from Pat Hyer on new graduate degree proposals
  - Minutes from meeting
- Curriculum Task Force listserv Mar-May 1995 (Box-folder 2-48)
- Collaboration Task Force 1994 (Box-folder 2-49)
  - Charge of the committee
  - Directory of members of the Collaboration Committee
  - Summary of committee meeting (from Harris)
  - Survey from Collaboration Committee to COE faculty
  - Results from faculty survey
  - Field notes from Mountain Lake retreat
  - Draft of the Collaboration Task Force report (with revisions in brackets)
  - Survey from committee to COE faculty
  - Agenda for Collaboration Committee meeting
  - Summary of task force meeting
- Correspondence with alumni and others on restructuring Summer 1994 (Box-folder 2-50)
- Letters to superintendents 1994 (Box-folder 2-51)
  - Memo from AACTE to "Chief Institutional Representatives"
  - "Opportunities for Schools, Colleges and Departments of Education"
  - Letter from dean
- Salary adjustments 1994 (Box-folder 2-52)
  - Memos on "Merit Raises and Structural Adjustments"
  - Memo from Worner on salary adjustments
- Money for "transition costs" 1994 (Box-folder 2-53)
- Program area work plans 1994 (Box-folder 2-54)
  - Draft plans for Instructional Technology and Educational Psychology
  - Program planning documents, All COE Programs
- Memos Jul 20 1994 (Box-folder 2-55)
- Classified staff issues 1994 (Box-folder 2-56)
  - Lists of staff in college divisions
  - Memo from Worner on restructuring
- Faculty 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2-57)
- Procedures for program elimination 1994 (Box-folder 2-58)
  - Memo from Harris and Lewis: "Procedures for Closing Programs Targeted for Elimination"
  - Memo from Worner: "Follow-up on Survey of Students in Programs Being Closed"
- Reports and materials Jul 1994 (Box-folder 2-59-59a)
  - Memo from Worner on plan and meeting
  - Draft of restructuring plan
  - Restructuring plan
  - Appendices to restructuring plan
  - Michele Connolly's notes from meeting
- Responsibility centers and additional reversions 1994 (Box-folder 2-60)
  - Memo from Carlisle to Worner
- LASc/middle school option 1994 (Box-folder 2-61)
  - Letter from E. Creamer to Worner
  - Letter from Worner, [memo from Lalik on LASc/middle school option attached]
- College of Education faculty meeting 1994 (Box-folder 2-62)
  - Agenda
  - Minutes (Glasson)
- Advisory Council on Strategic Budgeting and Planning 1994 (Box-folder 2-63)
  - Memo from Worner on request to use ACSBP as review mechanism
  - Formal request from Worner to use council as review mechanism
  - Partial transcript of meeting Sep 7 1994
- Adult education privatization and termination plans 1994 (Box-folder 2-64)
- Memos Sep 1994 (Box-folder 2-65)
  - Meeting Sep 30 1994
  - Memo announcing schedule revision
  - Handout on purpose of the university-level review
  - Flowchart tracking "plan"
- Rosters for Units A and B 1994 (Box-folder 2-66)
- Unit A 1994 (Box-folder 2-67)
  - Memo on April 26 meeting of Teacher Preparation Group
  - Memo from Stewart and Niles on "getting organized"
  - Memo from Stewart and Niles on "organizational matters"
  - Memo from Magliaro on conversations about future direction of department
  - Ballot for chair election
- Unit B 1994 (Box-folder 2-68)
  - Agenda / minutes from meeting (Tom Hunt)
  - Memo from Earthman on organizational plan for Unit B
  - Memo from Jimmie Fortune on reorganization consideration
  - Memo from Ed. Admin. electing to join Unit B
  - Memo from Career and Occupational Studies faculty electing to join Unit B
  - Memo from Counselor Education / Student Affairs electing to join Unit B
- Dean's support staff 1994 (Box-folder 2-69)
  - Report and justification on Dean's support staff
  - Memo from Worner on support staffing for interim programs
- Budget numbers 1990-1993 (Box-folder 2-70)
  - C&I budget 1989-1990
  - C&I budget 1990-1991
  - FY93 research expenditures for university
- Project ENABLE 1994 (Box-folder 2-71)
  - "The Enabler" vol. 1 (2)
  - Spectrum article
- Governor Allen's policies 1994 (Box-folder 2-72)
  - Announcements
  - Memo on exemptions to Executive Order 38
- Vito Perrone talk Oct 28 1994 (Box-folder 2-73)
  - Flyer announcing talk and introducing Perrone
- Old folks retreat 1994 (Box-folder 2-74)
  - Memo from Cathy Metcalf to participants, details on meeting time and place
- Merger talks between College of Education and College of Human Resources 1994 (Box-folder 2-75)
  - Memo from Worner on sharing restructuring and Phase II plans
  - Spectrum article on Carlisle's memo
- Meeting with University Rewards Committee 1994 (Box-folder 2-76)
  - E-mail announcing meeting
  - E-mail reminder of meeting
  - Notes from meeting (Nespor)
- Worner's memo on capital campaign Aug 1994 (Box-folder 2-77)
- Reduction in force policies 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2-78)
  - Memo from Woodard on layoff planning
  - Memo from Sherman to Worner on AUUP downsizing policy
  - Proposed changes in faculty handbook 2.10.3
  - Policy Memorandum 146 - Revision of RIF Policy Aug 8 1994
  - Memo: Sherman RIF policy
  - Memo from Don Creamer on Committee on Faculty Affairs: "Deliberations on Involuntary Separation Policies" Nov 12 1994
  - Memo from Sherman: draft of RIF policies Mar 3 1995
- Retirement buyout plans 1994 (Box-folder 2-79)
  - Memo from Hyer on "Faculty Retirement / Buyout Plan"
  - Draft of "Individual Transition Option Plan: VPI&SU"
- Executive Committee minutes 1988-1996 (Box-folder 2-80)
- Faculty Senate minutes 1993-1994 (Box-folder 2-81)
- Report of Ad Hoc Review Committee 1994 (Box-folder 2-82)
- Board of Visitors "Approval of Plan" 1994 (Box-folder 2-83)
- Memo extending Worner's appointment as dean Dec 1994 (Box-folder 2-84)
- Restructuring plans from Virginia Tech and other Virginia universities 1994 (Box-folder 2-85)
  - "Appendix: Restructuring Criteria"
  - "Restructuring Virginia Tech"
  - "Addendum to VT's Restructuring Plan"
  - "Virginia's Plan: Preparing for the 21st Century"
  - Plans of Mary Washington, George Mason, William & Mary, and Virginia Commonwealth University
  - Related Spectrum article Nov 17 1994
- College of Education restructuring plans 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2-86)
  - "Plan for Restructuring the College of Education"
  - E-mail from Worner: "Therefore be it resolved" (notification of Board of Visitors approval of restructuring plan)
  - E-mail from Worner - "Initiatives"
  - Memo from Worner - "Progress report"
- Curriculum Task Force materials 1995 (Box-folder 2-87)
- Governance and Organization Task Force materials 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2-88)
- College of Education faculty meeting 1995 (Box-folder 3-89)
  - Agenda
  - Annual report to faculty
  - Summary of Executive Committee meetings 1994-1995
- Mountain Lake College of Education retreat 1995 (Box-folder 3-90)
- College of Education promotions and tenure concerns 1993-1995 (Box-folder 3-91)
- International programs in the College of Education 1995 (Box-folder 3-92)
- Partnerships with the public schools 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3-93)
- Memos - Dean Worner 1994 (Box-folder 3-94)
- Tom Sherman - "A Proposal for Change" 1995 (Box-folder 3-95)
- College of Education faculty meeting 1995 (Box-folder 3-96)
  - Agenda
  - Memo - "Report of the adhoc faculty committee to review the College of Education restructuring plan"
  - Memo from Worner - "Progress report and memorandum of understanding" Feb 28 1994
- E-mail - "College vision" Feb 9 1995 (Box-folder 3-97)
- E-mail - "Workforce Transition Act" Mar 6 1995 (Box-folder 3-98)
- College of Education and College of Human Resources Merger Committee Apr 1995 (Box-folder 3-99)
- Dave Hutchins - "Ideas on the revitalized College of Education" 1995 (Box-folder 3-100)
- College of Education faculty meetings Aug 1995 (Box-folder 3-101)
  - Memo from Worner - "Restructuring: next steps"
  - List of "Issues, concerns, future goals, 1995-1996" distributed at COE meeting
  - Memo from Worner - "More on restructuring: next steps" Aug 18 1995
- College of Education program review 1995 (Box-folder 3-102)
  - Memo from Worner - "Program review processes and procedures"
  - Number of teaching certificates earned 1991-1995
  - Table of admissions requirements, EdD, PhD, Masters by degree area
  - Memo from Worner - "Program review: fine tuning"
- College of Education constitution 1995-1998 (Box-folder 1-103)
  - Memo - Terry Wildman: "Thoughts on the constitution"
- Tom Hunt - "The College of Education at Virginia Tech, 1971-1991" n.d. (Box-folder 3-104)